Register of the Garip Sultan papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Garip Sultan papers
1907-2010
2016C6
Hoover Institution Archives
25 manuscript boxes, 8 oversize boxes (20.5 linear feet)
Writings, correspondence, memoranda, printed matter, and sound recordings relating to Radio Liberty broadcasting to Tatarstan and Bashkortostan.
Sultan, Garip
Access
The collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2015.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1923 September 25 Born, Sterlitamak-Zirgan, Bashkir Autonomous Republic, the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics (USSR)
1939 Graduated from Tatar-Bashkir High School in Ishimbai, Bashkir Autonomous Soviet Socialistic Republic (ASSR)
1939-1941 Studied at Bashkir State Pedagogical Institute in Ufa
1941 Joined the Red Army
1942 Became prisoner of war and joined with the Tatar Legion; later served as a propagandist in the Tatar Liaison office
1945 Appointed as a head of the military department of the Tatar provisional government
1946-1947 Employed by the United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Administration (UNRRA) to work in the displaced persons camp at Mittenwald, Germany as the chief of the Camp Criminal Police
1951 Graduated from the Department of Law and Political Science at the University of Hamburg, West Germany
1951-1953 Doctoral candidate (Soviet constitutional law) at University of Munich
1953-1957 Appointed writer-producer at Radio Liberty, Tatar-Bashkir Service in Munich
1957 Arrived in the United States
1957-1968 Senior editor-writer and commentator in Radio Liberty’s New York office
1968-1987 Transferred to the Munich office as a deputy chief-editor of the Tatar-Bashkir service
1988-1989 Director of the Tatar-Bashkir service
1989 Retired
2011 Died
Scope and Content of Collection
The Garip Sultan papers consist of correspondence, writings, notes, memoranda, transcripts of radio broadcasts and related materials, and printed matter pertaining to Sultan's long career at Radio Free Europe and Radio Liberty (RFE/RL). The bulk of the material is contained in the Radio Free Europe/Radio Liberty series and focuses on the history of RFE/RL and the effectiveness of its programs. The inclusion of a substantial number of sound recordings complements the series. Also of importance are documents in the Subject File relating to Sultan’s activities in the Tatar nationalists' efforts to reestablish an Idel-Ural state independent from the Russian Federation.
Radio Liberty.; Radio broadcasting, Tatarstan (Russia).; Radio broadcasting, Bashkortostan (Russia).; Audiotapes.
- Career File, 1947-2009 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Records relating to Sultan's Radio Free Europe/Radio Liberty (RFE/RL) service, arranged chronologically in groups corresponding to the original arrangement of the materials.
  - Documents relating to appointments, promotion, and change of duties, 1947-1988 (Box-folder 1: 1-3)
    Includes Radio Liberty employment certificate copies, curriculum vitae, and photographs.
  - Personnel Action Reports, Radio Liberty, Inc., 1953-1989 (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - Articles, interviews, and notes regarding Sultan's career, 1960-2009 (Box-folder 1: 5-8)
    Includes materials relating to the celebration of Sultan's 80th and 85th birthdays in 2003 and 2008.
  - Certificate of honorable service upon retirement from RFE/RL, 1989 (Box-folder 1: 9)
    Includes correspondence.
- Correspondence, 1943-2006 (Boxes 1-2)
  - General, 1943-2003
    - 1943-1959 (Box-folder 1: 10)
    - 1960-1967 (Box-folder 1: 11)
    - 1970-1977 (Box-folder 1: 12)
    - 1980-1989 (Box-folder 2: 1)
    - 1990-1999 (Box-folder 2: 2)
    - 2000-2003 (Box-folder 2: 3)
  - Agi, Farit, 2000 (Box-folder 2: 4)
  - Broxup, Marie, 1985-1989 (Box-folder 2: 5)
  - Crawford, Thomas, 2005 (Box-folder 2: 6)
  - Davletbaev, Remin, 1991-1992 (Box-folder 2: 7)
  - Farkhshatov, Marsil, 2002-2005 (Box-folder 2: 8)
  - Galim, Enver, 1953-1987 (Box-folder 2: 9-11)
    Includes writings by Galim.
  - Iurkova, Klara, 1992-1993 (Box-folder 2: 12)
  - Kamenskaia, Zul'fira, 1992-1993 (Box-folder 2: 13)
  - Karamysh, Iuldoz, 1990 (Box-folder 2: 14)
  - Khalim, Aidar, 2001 (Box-folder 2: 15)
  - Kurat, Akdez, 1962-1966 (Box-folder 2: 16)
  - Lazzerini, Edward, 1982-1983 (Box-folder 2: 17)
  - Matuszewski, Daniel C., 1992-1993 (Box-folder 2: 18)
  - Meining, Stefan, 2005-2006 (Box-folder 2: 19)
  - Mühlen, Patrik, 1968-1998 (Box-folder 2: 20)
  - Nasyrov, R. G., 2000 (Box-folder 2: 21)
  - Ottmair, Rudolf, 1991 (Box-folder 2: 22)
  - Petersen, Jan Paul, 2004 (Box-folder 2: 23)
  - Rooy, Silvio van, 1961-1962 (Box-folder 2: 24)
  - Sabirova, L., 2001 (Box-folder 2: 25)
  - Sultanov, Abdul, 1992-1999 (Box-folder 2: 26)
  - Sultanov, Fanis, 1992-1998 (Box-folder 2: 27)
  - Sultanov, Midkhad, 1992-1997 (Box-folder 2: 28)
  - Tatar Watan Society, 1992-1994 (Box-folder 2: 29)
  - Vagizova, Venera, 2003-2004 (Box-folder 2: 30)
  - Verneye, Pierre C. T., 1974 (Box-folder 2: 31)
  - Werner, Ludwig, 1996-2003 (Box-folder 2: 32)
- Speeches and Writings, 1952-1984 (Boxes 3-4)
  Arrangement Statement
  Arranged chronologically.
  - "O nekotorykh izmeneniiakh semeinogo prava v SSSR," Azat Vatan, Munich, 1952 (Box-folder 3: 1)
  - SSSR segodnia i zavtra, conference speeches, Institute for the Study of the History and Culture of the USSR, Munich, 1953-1960 (Box-folder 3: 2-4)
  - Ayaz Ishaki Idilli, 1955 (Box-folder 3: 5)
  - "The Great Experiment After Forty Years," Trade Union Courier, 1957 (Box-folder 3: 6)
  - Brief Notes on the Muslim Peoples of the USSR for the Delegates of the Fifth World Moot of the Motamar E-Alam-E Islami at Baghdad, 1962 May 29-June 3 (Box-folder 3: 7)
  - "Modern Forms of Colonialism,", 1962 (Box-folder 3: 8)
  - "Moral and Spiritual Significance of Ramadan,", 1962 (Box-folder 3: 9)
  - "National Reaction of Tatars to Soviet Polices,", 1962 (Box-folder 3: 10)
    Includes correspondence regarding the 16th Annual Conference of the Middle East Institute.
  - Soviet Asiatic Writers and the Problem of Free Creativity: Materials for the Second Conference of Asian and African Writers in Cairo, Egypt, prepared by Garip Sultan, 1962 (Box-folder 3: 11-12)
    Includes correspondence and clippings.
  - Antireligious Activities in the Soviet Union: Hearings Before the Subcommittee on Europe of the House of Representatives Committee on Foreign Affairs (statement of Garip Sultan, President, American Islamic Association), 1965 (Box-folder 4: 1)
  - Müslüman-Arap Dünyasinda Sovyet Propagandasinn Dis Sekilleri, 1966 (Box-folder 4: 2)
  - Demographic and Cultural Trends Among Turkic Peoples of the Soviet Union, The Institute of East European Jewish Studies, 1968 (Box-folder 4: 3)
    Includes correspondence, conference material, and clippings.
  - "Idil-Ural Türklerinin Durumu," Emel, 1970 (Box-folder 4: 4)
  - "The Mission of Our Tatar-Bashkir Service: An Interview with Chief Editor Garip Sultan," William F. Robinson, RFE Research, A Magazine for Employees of Radio Free Europe & Radio Liberty, No. 4, 1984 (Box-folder 4: 5)
  - Drafts, 1965-1977 (Box-folder 4: 6-13)
- Subject File, 1926-2010 (Boxes 5-14)
  Arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Accusation of Mr. Sultan by the Soviets concerning the case of Musa Djalil, correspondence and printed matter, 1977-2004 (Box-folder 5: 1)
  - Akish, Alijuliah (Ali), 1970-1985 (Box-folder 5: 2-3)
    Includes correspondence, memoranda, reports, and writings.
  - All-Pakistan Political Science Association, Karachi, 1961-1962 (Box-folder 5: 4)
    Includes correspondence, statement, and program.
  - Almanya' Daki Kirim Tatar Cemiyeti, 1984-2009 (Box-folder 5: 5)
    Correspondence, event program, and printed matter. Includes “Orthodox Christian Qumans and Tatars of the Crimea in the 13th-14th Centuries,” by István Vásáry.
  - American Association for the Advancement of Slavic Studies, 1996-2000 (Box-folder 5: 6)
    Includes correspondence and financial documents.
  - Antibolshevik Bloc of Nations (ABN), 1951-1961 (Box-folder 5: 7)
    Includes correspondence, printed matter, clippings, and photographs.
  - Anti-religious activities in the Soviet Union and in Eastern Europe, 1962-1966 (Box-folder 5: 8-9)
    Includes correspondence, memoranda, and clippings.
  - Association for Central Asian Studies, 1985-1990 (Box-folder 5: 10)
    Includes correspondence and conference program.
  - Atasever, Ahmet Naim, 1984-1986 (Box-folder 5: 11)
    Includes correspondence, writings, and employment file.
  - Badretdinov, Sabirzyan, 1986-2001 (Box-folder 5: 12-13)
    Includes correspondence, employment file, writings, and clippings.
  - Bairamova (Bayramova), Fauziia (Fevzie), 1990-2010 (Box-folder 6: 1-2)
    Includes correspondence, writings, clippings, and printed matter.
  - Captive Nations Committee Germany/Europe (C.N.C. G/E), 1963-1989 (Box-folder 6: 3)
    Includes press releases and correspondence.
  - Captive Nations Week, 1960-1965 (Box-folder 6: 4)
    Scope and Contents ntoe
    Includes correspondence, printed matter, and a photograph depicting Alfred Korn.
  - Devlet, Nadir, 1979-1987 (Box-folder 6: 5)
    Includes correspondence and memoranda.
  - Davletshin (Dawletschin), Tamurbek, 1979-2004 (Box-folder 6: 6)
    Includes correspondence, autobiography, and other writings.
  - East Bible Institute, Stockholm, 1973-1975 (Box-folder 6: 7)
    Includes correspondence, printed matter, and notes.
  - Eidi, Taufik, 1989-2000 (Box-folder 6: 8-10)
  - European Liaison Group, London, 1984-1985 (Box-folder 6: 11)
    Includes correspondence and brochure.
  - First Meeting of Muslim Refugees from the USSR, New York, 1960-1963 (Box-folder 7: 1-4)
    Includes minutes, speeches, correspondence, photographs, and printed matter.
  - Giliazov, Iskander, 1995-1996 (Box-folder 7: 5)
    Includes correspondence and writings.
  - Golden Horde, 1962-1981 (Box-folder 7: 6)
    Includes articles, essays, and notes.
  - Gülecyüz, Hayrettin, 1982-1987 (Box-folder 7: 7)
    Includes correspondence and employment file.
  - Hakimoglu, Ajas, 1983-1987 (Box-folder 7: 8)
  - Harvard Central Asia Forum, 1993-1998 (Box-folder 7: 9)
  - Health and medical news, collected articles, 1982-1996 (Box-folder 7: 10-11)
    Includes clippings, brochures, and notes.
  - Idel-Ural Legion, 1943-2000
    Arranged in two groups by document type, then chronologically.
    - Research material, 1943-2009
      Includes correspondence, articles, clippings, and notes.
      - General, 1943-2009 (Box-folder 8: 1-8)
      - Photographs by H. Phillips, Bundesarchiv, printed copies, 1943-1945 (Box-folder 8: 9)
      - Hoffman archives copies, 1943-1946 (Box-folder 8: 10)
      - "B. Arch/Wienhold" documents copies, 1944-1945 (Box-folder 8: 11)
      - "Nürnberger Dokumente (Kopien im Institut für Zeitgeschichte),", 1946 (Box-folder 8: 12)
    - Printed matter, 1944-1949
      - Ansprache in Tätigkeitsbericht der Herrn Schafi-Almas aus der ersten Tagung der Idel-Ural-Türk-Tataren in Greifswald am 4. Marz 1944 (Box-folder 8: 13)
      - Idel-Ural Qorultay, Idel-Ural terek-tatarlarinin milli keras beriege prezidium, Berlin, 1944 (Box-folder 8: 14)
      - Tatar Adabiat, No. 4, Berlin, 1944 (Box-folder 8: 15)
      - "Geschichte der Turkestanischen Freiwilligen,", circa 1948 (Box-folder 8: 16)
  - Idel-Ural State, 1933-2010 (Box-folder 9: 1-13)
    Includes journal articles, research notes, galley pages, and drafts authored by Garip Sultan, as well as clippings, maps, and other printed matter.
  - Institut zür Erforschung der UdSSR e. V., 1954-1973 (Box-folder 10: 1)
  - Iskhaki, Ayaz, 1952-1990 (Box-folder 10: 2-3)
    Includes correspondence, biographical clippings, and other printed matter.
  - Islamic Council of Europe, 1978-1979 (Box-folder 10: 4)
    Includes correspondence, a memo, and a program of international conferences.
  - Mende, Gerhard von, 1947-2005 (Box-folder 10: 5-8)
  - The Middle East Institute, Washington, D.C., 1945-1962 (Box-folder 10: 9)
    Includes general information, members list, correspondence, conference opening speech, and notes.
  - Minai, Naile, 1982-1984 (Box-folder 10: 10)
  - "My Political Activities against Communism under Supervision of the Political Department (Special Projects) of the Radio Liberty Committee,", 1961-1999 (Box-folder 10: 11)
    Includes reports, correspondence, and clippings.
  - National Self-Determination: Its Successes and Failures, conference, Institute of Ethnic Studies, Georgetown University, Washington, D.C., 1959 (Box-folder 10: 12)
  - New Union of the Struggle for Independence of the Turko-Tatar of Idel-Ural, 1947-1971 (Box-folder 10: 13-14)
  - New York World's Fair, 1964-1965 (Box-folder 10: 15)
    Includes Folk Festival program, correspondence, and clippings.
  - Permanent International Altaistic Conference, 1972-2004 (Box-folder 10: 16)
  - Pilgrimage to Mecca, 1956 (Box-folder 11: 1-2)
    Includes correspondence, reports, clippings, and photographs.
  - "Possible Action in the Present Stage of East-West Relations," Groupe de Paris discussion, Munich, 1983 (Box-folder 11: 3)
  - Resuloglu, Nuri, 1984-1986 (Box-folder 11: 4)
  - Sakmari, Naile Nergis, 1986 (Box-folder 11: 5)
    Includes correspondence, employment file, and memoranda.
  - Scottish League for European Freedom, 1949-1950 (Box-folder 11: 6)
    Includes correspondence, clippings, and photographs relating to "The Convention of Delegates from the Resistance Movements in Europe and Asia."
  - Seymuratova, Ayshe, 1980-1984 (Box-folder 11: 7)
  - Shabayeva-Lensen, Rumija, 1979-1985 (Box-folder 11: 8)
    Includes correspondence, curriculum vitae, and writings.
  - Society for Central Asian Studies, 1985-1990 (Box-folder 11: 9)
    Includes correspondence and printed matter.
  - Sovereignty of the Republic of Tatarstan, 1977-2000 (Box-folder 11: 10-11)
  - "The State of Ethnic Minorities in the Soviet Union," conferences of Institute of East European Jewish Affairs, 1964-1970 (Box-folder 11: 12)
  - Sultan-Galiev, Mirsaid, 1929-1990 (Box-folder 11: 13-14)
    Includes clippings and other printed matter.
  - Tatar language, 1926-2007 (Box-folder 12: 1-9)
    Includes correspondence, writings, and clippings, as well as The Evolution of the Muslim Nationalities of the USSR and Their Linguistic Problem, by Alexandre Bennigsen and Chantal Quelquejay, 1961.
  - Tatarisch-Baschkirischer Kulturverein e.V. Berlin, 2001-2010 (Box-folder 12: 10-11, 13: 1-5)
    Includes program, activities report, correspondence, printed matter, and clippings.
  - Türk Kültürünü Arastırma Enstitüsü, Ankara, 1965-1971 (Box-folder 13: 6)
    Includes correspondence, conference program, and memoranda.
  - Turko-tatar broadcast of the Voice of America, 1951-1970 (Box-folder 13: 7)
    Includes correspondence, photographs, and press releases.
  - Unglaube, Heinz, 1944-1998 (Box-folder 13: 8-11, 14: 1-2)
    Includes Unglaube's memoir, correspondence, and clippings.
  - Union of Émigré Youth of the Peoples of the USSR in Munich, 1959-1960 (Box-folder 14: 3-4)
    Includes correspondence, reports, and printed matter, as well as Sultan's certificate as the authorized representative of the organization in the United States.
  - Ural, Ferit, 1984 (Box-folder 14: 5)
    Includes correspondence, memoranda, and employment file.
  - Wahlroos, Feride Bicuri, 1978-1988 (Box-folder 14: 6)
    Includes correspondence, memoranda, and writings.
  - World Congress of Tatars, 1989-1993 (Box-folder 14: 7-10)
    Includes organization's decree, correspondence, invitation, program, and clippings.
  - World Muslim Congress conferences, 1962-1964
    - Fifth conference at Baghdad, 1962 (Box-folder 14: 11-16)
      Includes programs, list of participants, speeches and reports by Sultan, correspondence, photographs, and clippings.
    - Sixth conference at Mogadishu, 1964 (Box-folder 14: 17)
      Includes invitation and program.
- Radio Free Europe/Radio Liberty File, 1907-2005 (Boxes 15-24)
  Arranged alphabetically by physical form or subject.
  - 40th and 50th anniversaries of radio broadcast, 1993, 2003 (Box-folder 15: 1-2)
  - "Central Asia: The Decades Ahead," Radio Liberty conference, program and correspondence, 1985 (Box-folder 15: 3)
  - History of Radio Free Europe/Radio Liberty, 1951-1997 (Box-folder 15: 4)
    Includes writings, clippings, memoranda, and notes.
  - General memoranda, 1983-2002 (Box-folder 15: 5)
  - Printed matter, 1954-2003 (Box-folder 15: 6-10)
  - Research Institute, establishment, 1990-1991 (Box-folder 16: 1)
  - Tatar-Bashkir language service, 1907-2005
    - Broadcast scripts, 1957-2002 (Box-folder 16: 2-10, 17: 1-9)
    - Correspondence, 1951-1997 (Box-folder 18: 1-3)
      Includes letters of support from the Republic of Tatarstan, 1993.
    - Council of Editors' meetings file, 1976-1989 (Box-folder 18: 4-10)
      Includes index of subjects discussed, minutes, resolutions, memorandum, and photographs.
    - Memoranda, 1962-1994 (Box-folder 19: 1-7)
    - Personnel files, 1981-1988 (Box-folder 19: 8-11)
    - Professional development training and workshop by Garip Sultan, 1948-1989
      - General, 1962-1989 (Box-folder 20: 1-7)
        Includes program, correspondence, memoranda, printed matter, and notes.
      - Photographs depicting participants during the training, 1967 (Box-folder 20: 8)
      - The Radio Announcer's Handbook, by Ben G. Henneke, 1948 (Box-folder 20: 9)
    - Radio broadcastings review by the Soviet press, 1974-1999 (Box-folder 22: 1-6)
      Includes clippings and press releases.
    - Research material, 1907-2005 (Box-folder 21: 7-11, 22: 1-12, 23: 1-10, 24: 1-3)
      Includes clippings, printed matter, writings, and notes collected for broadcast scripts.
- Writings by Others, 1907-2005 (Boxes 24-25)
  Arranged alphabetically by author.
  - Alishaqi (Elisxaqi), Mokhammed (Moxemmed), 1907 (Box-folder 24: 4)
  - Battal, A., 1926 (Box-folder 24: 5, 25: 1)
  - Burnas, Fatkhi (Fatxi), circa 1920 (Box-folder 25: 2)
  - Cagatay, Saadet, 1958-1965 (Box-folder 25: 3)
  - Gerey, Ahmed, 1964 (Box-folder 25: 4)
  - Giliazov, Iskander, 2005 (Box-folder 25: 5)
  - Gubaidullin, G., 1923 (Box-folder 25: 6)
  - Ibrahimov, Galimzhan, 1927 (Box-folder 25: 7)
  - Kurat, Akdes Nimet, 1969 (Box-folder 25: 8)
  - Sejfi, Abruj, 1927 (Box-folder 25: 9)
  - Validef, Gamalettdin, 1912 (Box-folder 25: 10)
- Oversize Material, 1937-1999 (Box 26)
  Arranged by physical form and chronologically thereunder.
  - Maps, 1937-1996, undated
    - The Mongol Empires in the 13th-14th Centuries (Golden Horde), 1937, 1996, undated (Box-folder 26: 1)
    - Imperial and Soviet Russian Expansion in Asia, 1944-1964, undated (Box-folder 26: 2)
    - Skizze d. Qypcaqs v. Bertold Spuler, circa 1949 (Box-folder 26: 3)
    - Union der Sozialistischen Sowjetrepubliken, undated (Box-folder 26: 4)
  - Newspapers, 1944-1999
    - Idel-Ural, Tatar legionan atnalaq gazitace, No. 28(85), 1944 (Box-folder 26: 5)
    - ABN Correspondence, monthly bulletin of the Antibolshevik Bloc of Nations, Nos. 5/6, 1955; 1/3-4/5, 8/9-10/12, 1956; 5/6, 11/12, 1957; 3/4-7/8, 1958, 1955-1958 (Box-folder 26: 6)
    - Trade Union Courier, America's leading labor newspaper, No. 19, 1957 (Box-folder 26: 7)
    - Aus Politik und Zeitgeschichte, 1960 April 20 (Box-folder 26: 8)
    - Magani Zhomga, No. 13, Nos. 27-28, 30-33, 1998-1999 (Box-folder 26: 9)
  - Tatar-Bashkir language service file, 1970-1989 (Box-folder 26: 10)
    Includes poster, photograph depicting transmitter towers, and Sultan's Certificate of Honour.
- Sound Recordings, 1967-1991, undated (Boxes 27-33)
  Includes records of RFE/RL broadcasts in the Tatar-Bashkir language. Arranged chronologically. Original descriptions on the reel boxes have been preserved.
  - 1/4 inch sound tape reels (175), 1967-1991
    - "Riza Fakretdin,", 1967 (Box-tape 28: 7)
    - 1968
      - "Tatar Music - Sophia Dawlet" (Box-tape 32: 21-25)
      - "Tatar - Bashkir Music" (Box-tape 33: 1-9)
    - "Contemporary Tatar Literature: A. Jeniki,", 1969 (Box-tape 30: 12)
    - "Ramazan Bajram,", 1972 (Box-tape 30: 19)
    - 1976
      - "Idegij" (Box-tape 28: 6)
      - "New Year Greetings of Staff Members of the Tatar-Bashkir Service" (Box-tape 29: 9)
      - "Tatar Music" (Box-tape 29: 22-24)
      - "Qorban Bairame" (Box-tape 31: 10)
    - "Qazannьn Jigilui,", 1978 (Box-tape 27: 1-2)
    - 1981
      - "Tatar Madaniate" (Box-tape 27: 13)
      - "Nuri Arslan" (Box-tape 31: 17)
    - 1982
      - "Sultangali" (Box-tape 29: 2)
      - "Fatih Husni" (Box-tape 30: 4)
    - 1983
      - "Qazannьn Jigiluina 431 Jьl Tulu Unajibelan 'Qazan'" (Box-tape 27: 17-18)
      - "R. Saffar, Ozaburi-Xan Macete" (Box-tape 28: 5)
      - "Poet Kol Gali's 800th Birthday Anniversary" (Box-tape 31: 6)
    - 1984
      - "Judidism" (Box-tape 27: 12)
      - "Idegäj" (Box-tape 32: 16)
    - 1985
      - "G. Ibrahikm's Book: Which Way Should Tatar Culture Go" (Box-tape 27: 3, 30: 8)
      - "G. Ibrakhim: 30th Anniversary of Rehabilitation - Memoirs of His Wife Prof. Mukhamadova" (Box-tape 27: 4)
      - "G. Ibrakhim: 30th Anniversary of Rehabilitation - A Classic and Victim of Stalinism A. Jeniky'" (Box-tape 30: 2-3)
      - "National Heritage - From History of National - Liberation Movement: G. Ibrakhim and the 90th Anniversary of His Publication 'Culpan Joldiz'" (Box-tape 27: 19)
      - "160th Birth Anniversary of Tatar Educator, Linguist, and Writer Q. Nasyri" (Box-tape 28: 3-4)
      - "Article in Literaturnaia Rossiia on Bashkir Poet Sh. Babich (Victim of Communism, Member of Bashkir Government in Orenburg)" (Box-tape 28: 16)
      - "Pedagogical Journal Bashkorstan Ugotougly Criticizes Our Analysis of the Soviet Language Policy" (Box-tape 28: 21)
      - "World War Two: On Central Publishing Houses Evacuated to Kazan: State of Tatar Book Publishing" (Box-tape 28: 22)
      - "Bashkir Poet Babich's 90th Birth Anniversary: First Victim of Communism" (Box-tape 28: 24)
      - "National Poet Ğabdulla Tuqay Anniversary - Literary Musical Show" (Box-tape 29: 10-14)
      - "National Chronology - The Millet Madjlese and Declaration of Idel-Ural State" (Box-tape 29: 15-21)
      - "Dramatist and Scholar N. Isanbet on Studying of History, Literary Heritage" (Box-tape 30: 5, 30: 13)
      - "Writer N. Isanbet - Author of Prohibited Historical Dramas, Specialist on Tatar Folklore Studies (90th Birth Anniversary)" (Box-tape 30: 6)
      - "Salient Features of Islam: 'The Sacrifice' - Religious and Social Meaning" (Box-tape 30: 16)
      - "Al-Hajj-Pilgrimage to Mecca: Its Religious and Social Meaning" (Box-tape 30: 17)
      - "Literary Journal Kazan Utlary on World War II and the Tatar Contribution to Victory" (Box-tape 31: 3)
      - "The 1063rd Anniversary of the Embracing of Islam in Tatar-Bashkiria" (Box-tape 31: 4, 32: 1-4)
      - "New Trend in Tatar Literature - Historical Novel and Political Limitations" (Box-tape 31: 5)
      - "The 68th Anniversary of the First All-Russian Moslem Congress in Moscow" (Box-tape 31: 11-16)
      - "41st Anniversary of the Deportation of Crimean-Tatars - A Historical-Literary Show, Nuri Arslan's Poem 'On the Shore of the Black Sea'" (Box-tape 31: 18)